בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
We begin today מסכת נזיר. Maseches Nazir. Today's דף Daf is נזיר
ב' עמוד א'. Nazir Beis Amud Aleph. Today is also the יארצייט
Yahrtzeit of my mother, חנה בת מרדכי אליעזר, Chana bas Mordechai Eliezer,
Anat Linzer, so this learning is in her memory and hopefully I'll
have a chance to say a few brief words at the end
of the דף Daf today, time permitting.
So we begin מסכת נזיר, Maseches Nazir, which logically continues מסכת נדרים.
Maseches Nedarim. We'll see in a minute in the גמרא Gemara how
the גמרא Gemara explains what this is doing in סדר נשים. Seder
Nashim. But the first word I'll just say before we jump right
in is that of course נזיר Nazir is a type of a
נדר. Neder. It is a status that is created through an act
of speech as we learned by נדר. Neder. נדר, Neder, as opposed
to a שבועה, Shavuah, is not a oath to do or to
not do something, but it is an act of speech that effects
the status of an object, makes an object forbidden, or a person
or the benefit of a person forbidden on another person.
And a נזיר Nazir is through an act of speech through which
not that you focus on what is forbidden, but an act of
speech that creates a status and defines a person as a נזיר.
Nazir. You obviously can only do this to yourself. Man or woman,
איש או אשה כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר. Ish o ishah ki
yafli lindor neder nazir. We actually had a few cases of a
woman taking a vow of נזירות Nezirus and her husband annulling it
in the last מסכת. Maseches. And the consequences of that status is
that a person cannot drink wine or actually any grapes or grape
products, etc., cannot become טמא Tamei to dead people, and has to
let his or her hair grow wild, his or her hair grow
wild.
And again, that's not an oath, that's not focusing on forbidding, it's
a status, the same way if you use your words to make
an animal into a קרבן, Korban, there are a lot of הלכות
Halachos that now apply to what is the status of an animal
that's a קרבן. Korban. One of them is you can't derive benefit,
you can't work it, you have to bring it as an, you
have to do certain things when you bring it to the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Here too, the focus is on instilling a status
through this act of speech. Okay, so let's take a look now
and the first משנה Mishnah here in נזיר Nazir very much parallels
the first משנה Mishnah in נדרים Nedarim to talk about what types
of speech acts are included in the act of becoming a, the
in the type of act that will make somebody into a נזיר.
Nazir. So let's take a look. כל כינויי... Kol Kinuyei... Oh, one
other thing I'll just say about the structure is, as opposed to
נדרים, Nedarim, where we did not have a normal תוספות, Tosfos, there
was a tiny little תוספות Tosfos running along the side, but it
wasn't a standard תוספות, Tosfos, not just in terms of size, but
in terms of that it was more of a like a commentary
than it was the type of a dialectic approach towards a critical
commentary of asking what about this גמרא Gemara and what about that
גמרא Gemara and working to find resolutions.
That's like the that standard genre of תוספות Tosfos is here now,
so you'll see you've got a nice standard-looking page with תוספות. Tosfos.
You do not have the ר"ן Ran because there's no real, there's
not the same need for a running commentary. However, to alert you
to the fact, רש"י Rashi is still not רש"י. Rashi. Okay. Who
רש"י Rashi is, I'm sure there's some scholarly discussion about it that
I did not get a chance to explore, but it is not
רש"י, Rashi,
but still because no רש"י? Rashi? Yeah, I think there was no
רש"י, Rashi, I don't know, I think there's no רש"י. Rashi. Because
there's no ר"ן, Ran, though, however, we probably will refer to רש"י
Rashi more often, because since תוספות Tosfos is more the standard תוספות,
Tosfos, you don't have as much of a running commentary on the
מסכת Maseches as we did in נדרים, Nedarim, although תוספות Tosfos does
a little bit of both here. There are תוספותים Tosfosim which are
more like a running commentary. But anyway, we probably will refer to
this pseudo-רש"י Rashi a little bit more. You also have the רא"ש
Rosh that does something of a running commentary. The other thing that
I should say, ironically, because the page looks like a more standard
page, is that the commentaries out there, there are fewer ראשונים Rishonim
outside of the page. By נדרים, Nedarim, you had רמב"ן Ramban wrote
an entire הלכות נדרים, Hilchos Nedarim, sort of, you know, to like
about that that sort of did, you know, sort of like doing
the same job that the רי"ף Rif did, and you know, that
the ר"ן Ran did on נדרים. Nedarim. It's actually in the back
here or whatever. This, I think this גמרא Gemara has it in
the back. Anyway, it doesn't matter. Yeah, so it's in the back
here, if you get around, if you have it, you know, you
have the רי"ף Rif wrote a רי"ף Rif on נדרים, Nedarim, the
רמב"ן Ramban wrote a הלכות נדרים Hilchos Nedarim of the רמב"ן Ramban
that parallels the רי"ף. Rif. There's a ריטב"א, Ritva, נמוקי יוסף, Nemuhei
Yosef, a רשב"א. Rashba. There's a lot of standard ראשונים Rishonim on
נדרים. Nedarim. There are not really too many ראשונים Rishonim on נזיר
Nazir because I don't know why. I mean, it's not just because
whether it's נוגע למעשה. Nogaya le-ma'aseh. It's true, probably many more people
take vows than they do
become a נזיר, Nazir, especially nowadays where there's no בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, so you can't end your נזירות. Nezirus. But since when did
the practical relevance of something determine whether there are going to be
ראשונים Rishonim on the מסכת? Maseches? So, just an interesting point, that
while the page is more normal, the ראשונים Rishonim that exist outside
of the page really much more on נדרים Nedarim than on
our מסכת. Maseches. that we're used to and there's some assumption that
maybe it was more from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, although as I
mentioned when we did נדרים, Nedarim, the standard scholar consensus right now
is that it probably came from a different ישיבה yeshiva in בבל,
Bavel, and that's the editing in that different ישיבה yeshiva center in
בבל Bavel reflects a slightly different type of idioms and a different
type of a language. Okay, not radically different, but you will see
some types of different languages here, different terms. Okay, so now let's
begin. כל כינויי נזירות כנזירות. Kol kinuyei nezirus kenezirus.
All of euphemisms or like sort of like parallel terms for a
נזיר Nazir count as a נזירות. nezirus. Even if it's not the
standard terminology, if it's some way of saying the term with a
different type of a phrase that also counts as well. We'll see
what that means in a minute, the משנה Mishna will explain. האומר,
Ha'omer, somebody says אהא, Ahei, I will be, without filling out the
line.
I'll be what I'll be. הרי זה נזיר. Harei zeh Nazir. That's
a נזיר. Nazir. Now, really? I mean, you could fill in that
blank with a million things. So the גמרא's Gemara going to say,
in a particular context where a נזיר Nazir is walking in front
of you and you said I will be, say like, that context
fills in the blank. או אהא נאה, O ahei na'eh, I will
be beautiful. Okay, now again, does נאה na'eh mean a נזיר? Nazir?
Now, נאה na'eh could be a parallel word to נזיר Nazir where
we're about to see words like נזיר, Nazir, נזיק, Nazik, נזיח, Naziach,
etc. So it could be like that, that somehow נאה na'eh was
a term that was understood to be a stand-in for the term
of נזיר. Nazir. But as opposed to the stand-in terms which are
a little bit nonsense terms, this actually seems like it actually means
נאה, na'eh, beautiful. So the גמרא Gemara will again say like this
first term of I will be that it's talking that the person
is basically holding onto his hair and saying אהא נאה. ahei na'eh.
So some type of a context makes us understand that that what
that means is I will be beautiful like a נזיר, Nazir, that
beautiful means he's assuming that a נזיר Nazir is beautiful. The גמרא
Gemara will discuss whether it's objectively so or not, but that's what
he's assuming, that's what he means by those words. Now, these two
terms are not are not כינויים, kinuyim, at least the first one
isn't. The first one is an uncompleted thought, an uncompleted sentence, I
will be, you'll be what? And that actually is something, if you
remember from נדרים, Nedarim, that is a יד. yad. יד Yad is
like a handle, which means it is an
uncompleted handle sort of gets you access to something without holding onto
the thing itself, without the thing being the thing itself. It's elliptical.
And therefore, that's another principle, that an elliptical sentence when it is
somehow there's enough context to understand how you would fill in the
blank, and we'll get into the גמרא Gemara what type of context
do you need,
how obvious that context has to be, that also works. That's considered
a יד. yad. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara will ask you, it's
just like the beginning of נדרים Nedarim which dealt with a יד
yad in the משנה Mishna but didn't use the term יד. yad.
Okay, so that's that. Now, it is possible that אהא נאה, ahei
na'eh, what does אהא נאה ahei na'eh mean? Is that a יד
yad or is that a כינוי? kinuy? It a little bit falls
between the two, right? It's not a יד yad because it's not
really elliptical, it's a whole sentence, I will be beautiful. Okay, great,
but what do you mean by that? I mean, so is that
now or though a כינוי kinuy is you say a full thing
but you almost say a stand-in word. Stand-in for the word נזיר
Nazir is נזיק, Nazik, נזיח. Naziach. We'll see that in a minute.
Okay, this is not a word that means נזיר Nazir with some
type of substitution. The word means beautiful, but the context, what do
you mean by beautiful? Oh, you mean you want to be a
נזיר. Nazir. So the תוספות Tosafot puts that into the יד yad
category, תוספות Tosafot and the ראש Rosh seem to put it in
the יד yad category, but it's a little interesting, a space between
a יד yad and a כינוי. kinuy. So we'll get back to
that. Okay, anyway, נזיר. Nazir. Now, the question is how do you
read the word נזיר Nazir here in the משנה? Mishna? One way
to read it is, if you say אהא ahei or you say
אהא נאה, ahei na'eh, you are a נזיר. Nazir. Okay,
that's one way to read it. The other way to read it
is, if somebody says I will be a נזיר, Nazir, נזיק, Nazik,
נזיח, Naziach, פזיח, Paziach, so everybody can see how those words are
like a little bit nonsense words but they're variations of the word
נזיר. Nazir.
Well, if you take the נון nun and you sort of make
a little קנייטש kniytsh you make it into a פא, pei, you
take the ריש reish and you draw a line you get from
נזיר Nazir you get to
פזיח. Paziach. הרי זה נזיר. Harei zeh Nazir. So that's a classic
כינוי, kinuy, a classic כינוי kinuy is that you're using some other
word that's a stand-in for the standard word that you would use.
Now, there's a debate in the גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim which
is whether this is לשון שבדו חכמים, lashon shebadu chachamim, is this
a language that the rabbis invented? Okay, some type of nonsense words
or whatever that the rabbis invented. Or is it לשון אומות? loshon
umos? Or is it some type of a different language, it's a
literally it's a vernacular or some other type of a
established language that's not just invented by the rabbis. It would be
pretty funny that there would be other languages that would have a
concept of נזיר Nazir and that the way they would, the words
that they would use for it would be these close,
these close parallels: נזיק, nazik, פזיח, paziach, etc. It certainly sounds like
it's more of some type of an inventive language than it's לשון
אומות. loshon umos. And yes, there's a whole discussion like if it's
לשון אומות loshon umos then why do you need to tell me
that then big deal, so you can say it in translation. And
if it's לשון שבדו חכמים, loshon shebadu chachomim, it becomes another question,
which is, well does that mean it's not really the language of
נזיר? Nazir? The ר"ן Ran in נדרים Nedorim said that even if
the rabbis invented it, once it becomes how that language is understood,
like there's no such thing as an objective idea of a language,
said the ר"ן Ran in נדרים. Nedorim. He said it's all convention.
So if people, even if the rabbis were the ones that originated
it, once that becomes the convention and people understand what it means,
then it becomes a language for נזירות. nezirut. Now why did they
invent such a language? The גמרא Gemara by נדרים Nedorim says that
if a person is too likely to say the classic word for
נדר, neder, you might to remind you the classic word for נדר
neder is קונם, Konam, which is, well, or קרבן. Korban. Okay, something
is like a קרבן Korban and therefore they created a substitute word
like קונם Konam or other things that were like קרבן. Korban.
And there the גמרא Gemara says it's that a person should not
start by saying קרבן Korban and say קרבן להשם Korban L'Hashem or
say להשם קרבן L'Hashem Korban and say God's name in vain. That's
really not a concern by נזיר. Nazir. Nobody's going to say נזיר
להשם, Nazir L'Hashem,
although the פסוק Pasuk says it, right? איש כי יפלא לנדר נדר
נזיר להזיר להשם. Ish ki yafli lindor neder nazir lehazir l'hashem. So
I don't know. But anyway, but it's less likely that somebody would
say הריני נזיר להשם. Hareini Nazir L'Hashem. Anyway, you wouldn't say להשם
נזיר L'Hashem Nazir probably. So it's less clear why, and it's probably
also more understandable that the rabbis wanted to create some sense of
like that this is like very serious and weighty. Right, so you
don't use if something you always have to use a substitute term
for, we say like השם, Hashem, we don't say God's name or
whatever, right? On the one hand you could say it makes it
too accessible because then everybody says השם השם השם Hashem Hashem Hashem
all the time, whereas if you had to say the real name
you would maybe hesitate more, right? But on the other hand you
understand that the actual thing is a weighty thing if you're using
a substitute term. So it seems like somehow related to that idea
that the rabbis wanted to somehow communicate the weightiness of this, they
developed this substitute type of a language. So these things also work
for being a נזיר. Nazir. I want to read to the end
and then I'll go back and say a few more things about
this, about this קונם. Konam.
הריני כזה, Hareini kaze, if you say I'm like this one and
presumably there's a נזיר Nazir in front of you. Or הריני מסלסל,
Hareini mesalsel, I will be like sort of like a twirler with
my hair, thank you. הריני מכלכל Hareini mechalkel which presumably means something
like מסלסל, mesalsel, you know, I will be sort of right like
playing with my hair. So הרי עלי לשלח פרע, harey alai l'shaleach
pera, I will cast my let my hair grow wild. So הרי
זה נזיר, harey ze nazir, that is a נזיר. Nazir. So that's
similar to הריני נאה, Hareini naeh, which it isn't that the word
itself somehow means נזיר, Nazir, but the context of what you're saying
is clear that you're saying that I'm going to become a נזיר.
Nazir. That is the, that is the meaning of that word in
context, not the word but of the phrase in context.
These are allusions with legal force.
Right. So it seems like כינויים, kinuim, the simple sense of כינוי,
kinuoy, יד yad is an incomplete sentence and a כינוי kinuoy is
either a substitute word or a phrase which doesn't literally mean something
but in the context that's what the phrase means. הרי זה נזיר.
harey ze nazir. הרי עלי ציפורין, harey alai tziporin, if I have
an obligation of bringing birds, which are the obligation of a נזיר
Nazir at the end of the נזירות. nezirut.
It's also an obligation of a מצורע. metzora.
Right, exactly. So he may, well you can't become a מצורע metzora
at a will. רבי מאיר אומר נזיר, Rabbi Meir omer Nazir, you're
a נזיר. Nazir. חכמים אומרים אינו נזיר, Chachamim omrim eino Nazir, you're
not. And we'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara. Now let me
say something about, let me say something about we'll see in the
גמרא. Gemara. Now let me say something about what, one more point
about this idea of כינויים. kinuim.
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, he says two
interesting things. There's תוספות Tosfos of נזיר Nazir right before the lines
get wide. He says like this,
he says,
ויש לומר, V'yesh lomar,
it is about ten lines before the lines get wide, it starts
with the word על הנזירות. al ha-nezirut. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9, 10, maybe about fourteen lines before the lines
get wide. Do people see that in the תוספות Tosfos here, נזיר?
Nazir? It's about, it's about literally halfway through. It is about literally
halfway down in the narrow column. תוספות Tosafot. *Tosfos* says, or of
the narrow column of their תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*. He says ויש לומר
*V'yesh lomar*. He says, what is the חידוש chiddush, *chidush* if it
is just a different language? So what do you have to tell
me that you can talk in another language? Of course it's true.
אין הכי נמי דגם בשאר לשונות אם הכיר והבין ונתכוון לקבל עליו
נזירות nezirus הוי נזיר nazir *Ein hachi nami d'gam b'sha'ar lishonot im
hikkir v'hevin v'nitkaven lekabel alav nezirut havei nazir*. Okay, it's true, right?
If you just said in any other language and that was your
intention, of course it would work. So why does the משנה Mishnah.
*Mishna* have to mention things like נזיח nazich, פזיח *Naziach Paziach* etc.
if all it is is a different language? So he says, אבל
הני לשני דמתניתין *aval hanei lishnei d'matnitin*, the terms in the משנה
Mishnah, *Mishna*, כי אמר נדרו באחד משלשה לשונות הללו *ki amar nidro
b'achad m'shlosha lishonot hallalu*, if you say you're a נזר *nezer* like
נזיק פזיק נזיח פזיח *Nazik Pazik Naziach Paziach*, okay, which even assuming
it's a different language, חייל עליה נזירות Nezirut, נמי כי אין מתכוין
*chayel alei nezirut nami ki ein mitkaven*, even if you didn't intend
for it to be משום דדמי טפי ולשון התורה מלשונות אחרין דלשון
התורה הוא נזיר nazir. *mishum d'dami tefai v'lashon haTorah milshonot acherin d'lashon
haTorah hu nazir*. Now this is crazy, because even if the guy
said הריני נזיר nazir *hareini nazir*, I just said הריני נזיר nazir,
*hareini nazir*, if you don't intend to be a נזיר nazir. *nazir*,
the words don't make you a נזיר nazir. *nazir*. The whole principle
there too, the whole principle is פיו ולבו שווים *piv v'libo shavin*.
You need the right intent. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says well, why
do you say these words? Because since these words are so close
to the formal תורה Torah *Torah* language, it binds you even if
you don't intend it. If you said it in French, in Hebrew,
in English, in any, Spanish, you'd have to intend it. But if
you say these words, which are close to the word נזיר nazir
*nazir* of the תורה Torah *Torah*, then you're bound even if you
don't intend it. But you're never bound if you don't intend even
if you say it in Hebrew. So, must, I really don't know
the answer, but it must mean that there's some middle space here.
Like what
if you just, I always have this interesting question. Like let's say
somebody doesn't know, people say like if you count ספירה *sefirah*, you
don't know what you're saying, you can't call it a counting of
ספירה *sefirah* if you don't know what the words mean. But let's
say you know that today is the third day and you know
that somehow this whole sentence is saying that today is the third
day, but you read it all in transliteration and you don't know
what any one of the words means. Is that still saying that
you knew what you were saying because you knew essentially what the
whole sentence was saying, right? So I wonder if that's what he
is saying, which is like somehow maybe if you're saying words that
to you are gobbledygook,
but you're like reading a French words and you don't know what
any individual word means, maybe it doesn't become a נזיר Nazir *nazir*
even though you want to be a נזיר Nazir *nazir*. Whereas here,
if you want to be a נזיר nazir. *nazir* and you're saying
it in the formal official language or in some close variation of
it, maybe that's good enough. So that's the best I can understand
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*. But what he's dealing with is the sense maybe
there's this formal language in Hebrew and this is just a slight
variation of it and that somehow is more binding than if you
were to say the whole thing in just a translation. But you
can't say you didn't intend it at all. That's clearly not true
if you didn't intend it at all.
פיו ולבו שווים *piv v'libo shavin*. There you go. So that's number
one. Now what's also interesting is ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*'s
idea that these are made-up words. So first of all, what we
need to know is that according to a number of ראשונים Rishonim
*Rishonim*, they disagree with the רן Ran *Ran* and they say it's
not true, that you can just make up your own convention like
saying I don't know, Pig Latin is a language. Since everybody understands
it, Pig Latin is a language. Is it really a language? Okay,
so that it's not really a language and therefore according to some
ראשונים *Rishonim*, you're not דאורייתא *d'Oraita* a נזיר Nazir *nazir*. You're only
דרבנן *d'Rabbanan* a נזיר Nazir *nazir*. Or, so then you can't maybe
can't bring קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. Or maybe it's some middle stage where
you get מלקות *malkut* but you're not enough to bring קרבנות korbanot
*korbanot*, which is weird, there's a middle level דאורייתא *d'Oraita*. But some
people ask that if this is really just a made-up language, maybe
it doesn't create a full נזירות Nezirut, *nezirut*. Again going to the
point. Now that's an easier point, that even if you intended it,
you might have to say the right words, right? And that's again
what we're going to be focusing on. You need the words. words
and you need the intent. So the first answer of תוספות Tosafot
was a חידוש, chiddush. read simply he's saying if you say the
words even without the intent, that's not true. He must mean that
you have some general intent even though you don't have a specific
one. But let's now look at the next line of תוספות. Tosafot
He says, וריש לקיש פליג התם, ve-Reish Lakish polig hatam, some ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish, just disagrees there, ואמר לשון שבדו חכמים מלבם, ve-amar
lashon shebadu chachamim milibam, it was a made-up language. והשתא פריך אמאי
בדינא הוא ותיקנו רבנן לשון כינויים והשיב דזימנין דבעי למימר להשם קרבן
ואמר להשם קונם ומפיק שם שמים לבטלה. ve-hashta parikh amai badina hu
ve-tiknu rabanan lashon kinnuyim ve-heshiv de-zimnin de-ba'ei lemeimar la-Hashem korban ve-amar la-Hashem
konam u-mapik shem shamayim le-vatalah. Okay, so that's the problem over there.
It's not really relevant here. לכך תיקנו כינויים שלא הורגל הלשון לומר
להשם קונם. lekakh tiknu kinnuyim shelo hurgal halashon lomar la-Hashem konam.
Fine. Now here's our key point: ואם תאמר לריש לקיש היכי מייתי
קרבן על ידי לשון שבדו חכמים, ve-im tomar le-Reish Lakish hekhi maytei
korban al yedei lashon shebadu chachamim, how can you bring a קרבן
korban
if this is all rabbinic? הקמייתי חולין בעזרה. ha-kamaytei chullin ba-azarah.
So again, as I mentioned, the ר"ן says once they made it
up, then it's a convention and then people understand it. But let's
see what תוספות Tosafot says. יש לומר כיון דמתכוין לנדור בנזיר ויודע
שלשון זה בדו חכמים לנדור בהם בנזיר קבלה גמורה הוא כאילו אמר
בלשון הכתוב בתורה. yesh lomar keivan de-mitkavein lindor be-nazir ve-yodeia she-lashon zeh
badu chachamim lindor bahem be-nazir kabbalah gemurah hu ke'ilu amar bi-lashon ha-katuv
ba-Torah. That's your intent, and this is the language that the rabbis
have selected לנדור בהם בנזיר, lindor bahem be-nazir, קבלה גמורה הוא כאילו
אמר בלשון הכתוב בתורה. kabbalah gemurah hu ke'ilu amar bi-lashon ha-katuv ba-Torah.
So then it really does fully count, okay, because that was your
intent and that's the meaning the rabbis assigned it. Now what's funny
about this תוספות Tosafot is the phrase כאילו אמר בלשון הכתוב בתורה.
ke'ilu amar bi-lashon ha-katuv ba-Torah.
Last I checked, there was no official text in the תורה Torah
of what is the word you have to say. So תוספות Tosfos
is again assuming like there's some formal text out there. So the
first part of תוספות says even if I don't understand it, it
binds me, which again you can't take too literally. But somehow if
I say the formal text it binds me. What formal text? You
made up a formal text? Here he says, right, that according to
ריש לקיש, even though it's invented terms, right, since it's your intent
plus the invented terms becomes essentially as if you said the formal
text. Again, one would ask, whoever said there was a formal text?
Okay, and then the last thing he says is maybe it doesn't
work completely. ורביה בר חייא פי' דריש לקיש לאו לענין
קרבן קאמר אלא לענין מלקות דלקי אבנזירות. ve-Ravya bar Chiya peirash de-Reish
Lakish lav le-inyan korban ka'amar ela le-inyan malkus de-laki a-nezirus. Okay, you
get lashes but you don't bring a קרבן. korban. Very interesting middle
stage. How could it be enough of a נזירות nezirot. to get
lashes if you transgress, but not enough to bring a קרבן? korban?
Okay, so very interesting questions here about how much is there a
formal language or not, and what happens with terms which are understood
but are not really part of a formal language. We're late, so
unless it's really pressing, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
מכדי, mikhdi, says the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look. תנא בסדר
נשים קאי. tana be-seder nashim ka-ei.
We are here in סדר נשים. Seder Nashim. מאי טעמא תני נזיר?
mai ta'ama tani nazir? Why
do—what does נזיר Nazir have to do with נשים? nashim? Now, the
easiest answer is, and sort of תוספות and the ראש, Rosh, תוספות
discusses this, is that it follows נדרים nedarim and it's a type
of a נדר. neder. Now, what does נדרים nedarim have to do?
Well, because of the—what we learned for the last two פרקים prakim
in נדרים, nedarim, because נדרים nedarim its primary place in the תורה—I
Torah mean there are two places, right, about לא יחל דברו ככל
היוצא מפיו יעשה. lo yakhel devaro ke-khol ha-yotzei mi-piv ya'aseh. But anyway,
or I think that is the same place, right, I'm sorry, but
another one of כי תחדל לנדור לא יהיה בך חטא. ki tekhdal
lindor lo yihyeh bekha cheit. Anyway, the primary place of נדרים nedarim
is in the תורה Torah focuses on the husband or the father's
right to annul the vows of his wife or of his daughter.
So that's really the primary place in the תורה Torah is around
husband and wife and father and daughter, which is about נשים. nashim.
And number two is also just like where else are you going
to put נדרים? nedarim? Like, you know, sometimes it's like you have
ששה סדרים, shisha sedarim, some things are going to have to force-fit,
like, I don't know where you'd, maybe, maybe more by נזיר. Nazir.
Anyway, so that's the simplest answer is that נזיר Nazir follows נדרים
nedarim and נדרים nedarim is in נשים. nashim. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. תנא קרא קאי. tana kra ka-ei. והיה אם לא
תמצא חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר. ve-hayah im lo timtza
chen be-einav ki matza bah ervat davar. Okay, this is about a
husband divorcing his wife because she found ערות דבר, ervat davar, a
matter of nakedness, which presumably means adultery. והכי קאמר, ve-hakhi ka'amar,
and this is what it says: מי גרם לה לעבירה יין, mi
garam lah la-aveirah yayin, what is going to cause her to sin?
Wine. וקאמר כל הרואה סוטה בקלקולה, ve-ka'amar kol ha-ro'eh Sotah be-kilkulah,
we're going to see that סוטה Sotah is going to follow נזיר,
Nazir, and anybody who sees a סוטה Sotah in her disgrace because,
you know, her hair disheveled and what she had to do and
so on, and presumably she did what she did because she was
drawn after wine and after the sensual world. So what should your
response be? יזיר עצמו מן היין, yazir atzmo min ha-yayin, you should
disavow yourself of wine. Now, of course, the irony is exactly that,
is that, you know, is that here it's still so totally talking
to a male audience that it doesn't say that a woman who
sees a woman who was led astray by wine should—should become a
נזירה, nezirah, which also could be. No, the man who sees the
woman led astray by wine, he should become a נזיר. Nazir, So
of course, you know, תוספות or whatever says, well, because she was
led astray by wine and presumably the man she was having the
affair with was also led astray by wine, so—so you shouldn't fall
in that, you, the man, become a נזיר. Nazir. But again, very
funny how it all gets translated through the male lens, you know,
where's the women who are responding to what this woman has done.
Anyway, because of that, therefore since it connects to גיטין Gittin and
it connects to סוטה Sotah and so on ultimately, and that and
נזיר Nazir and, you know, is... is sort of juxtaposed in the
תורה to מסכת סוטה, Masechet Sotah, which also seems to be the
point. Right here also סוטה Sotah comes next, and in the תורה
נזיר Nazir and סוטה Sotah are juxtaposed. So that's why it appears
here as well.
Okay. So, סוטה Sotah being a bad
thing is—well, that's a good point, and we will get to that.
We see the recurring theme in מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim is that
you're not supposed to take נדר, neder, it's a bad thing to
take a נדר. neder. We will see what the גמרא's Gemara attitude
is towards נזירות, nezirot, whether it is the same or not. Let's
take a look. Okay. פתח בכינויים ומפרש ידות. Patach be'kinuyim u'faresh yadot.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, "One minute. It said כל כינויי נזירות
כנזירות. kol kinuyei Nezirut ke'nezirut. It started with the idea of a
כינוי, kinuy, substitute words, but then it goes right into a יד,
yad, an elliptical sentence, אהא." ahei. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבא ואיתימא כדי, Amar Rava va'itayma kadei, Rava says and some say
anonymously it was said: חסורי מיחסרא והכי קתני. Hisurei mihasra ve'hachi katani.
It's missing some words, here's how you have to read the משנה.
Mishnah. Throw in the idea that of a יד yad as well.
כל כינויי נזירות כנזירות, Kol kinuyei Nezirut ke'nezirut, all substitute words for
נזיר Nazir counts as a נזירות, neziros, וידות נזירות כנזירות, ve'yadot nezirut
ke'nezirut, and also
truncated sentences also count. ואלו הן ידות, Ve'elu hein yadot, and here
are the ידות: yadot: אומר אהא הרי זה נזיר. Omer ahei harei
zeh nazir. Okay, so stick in the idea, we don't just mean
כינויים, kinuyim, we also mean ידות. yadot. So the גמרא Gemara says
if that's what you're going to do, ולפרוש כינויי ברישא. ve'lifrosh kinuyei
be'reisha. If you start by saying כל כינויים, kol kinuyim, even if
you want to stick in an idea of a יד, yad, the
first concrete examples you should give should be the כינויים. kinuyim. So
the גמרא Gemara says תנא מההוא דסליק הוא מפרש ברישא. Tana me'hahu
de'salik hu me'faresh be'reisha. No, since it said כינוי kinuy and it
said יד, yad, of course it didn't say יד, yad, we snuck
in the idea of יד, yad, but since in this parenthetical, implicit
way we're also saying יד, yad, we're going to talk about the
last thing we mentioned. Right, it's always a question: is—do you do
A-B-B-A, which is chiasmic, or do you do A-B-A-B? So the גמרא
Gemara says it's going to do A-B-B-A: כינוי, יד, יד, כינוי. kinuy
yad yad kinuy? So the problem is that—what? Didn't the נדרים Nedarim
start the—? Yes, exact same way. Okay, yeah, exact parallel with how
נדרים Nedarim starts. Okay, so anyway, but the funny thing is, is
that we're not really doing A-B-B-A because the first B was just
we're writing it into the משנה, it doesn't really exist in the
משנה. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
תנא מההוא דסליק הוא מפרש ברישא, Tana me'hahu de'salik hu me'faresh be'reisha,
as it taught, and I'll give you examples where we do A-B-B-A.
במה מדליקין ובמה אין מדליקין, Bameh madlikin u'vameh ein madlikin,
what can you light with and what can't you light with? ומפרש
אין מדליקין ברישא, U'me'faresh ein madlikin be'reisha, and it gives what you
cannot light with first. במה טומנין ובמה אין טומנין, Bameh tomnin u'vameh
ein tomnin, what can you insulate food with before שבת Shabbat and
what can't you? ומפרש אין טומנין, U'me'faresh ein tomnin,
it does the second one, it does A-B-B, okay, ברישא. be'reisha. במה
אשה יוצאה ובמה אינה יוצאה, Bameh isha yotza u'vameh eino yotza,
what can a woman wear on שבת Shabbat and what can she
not, what would be a carrying concern? ומפרש לא תצא
אשה U'me'faresh lo tetze isha with—starts with what she cannot wear ברישא.
be'reisha. Okay, so it's very classic that we do A-B-B-A. Okay, now
the funny thing is, I'm a little bit going to anticipate what
the גמרא Gemara is about to say, but the funny thing is
it—those things don't do A-B-B-A. You know what those things do? A-B-B.
It's not going to list every single thing you are allowed to
wear, right? Every little—every—every—thing under the sun that you are allowed to
use for candles on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. It's only going to
list the things that you can't. You can't list the infinite category
of things that you can, you're only going to list the things
that you can't. But anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says even if
it's not doing A-B-B-A, it's sort of going to pick up on
the second thing it said. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: "One minute, that's not always a
rule." והתנן: Ve'hasnan: במה בהמה יוצאה ובמה אינה יוצאה, Bameh behemah yotza
u'vameh eino yotza, what can an animal be sort of dressed with
and what can an animal not be dressed with on שבת, Shabbat,
what would be considered carrying in terms of the animal? ומפרש יוצא
גמל ברישא, U'me'faresh yotza gamal be'reisha, and then it gives things that
an animal is allowed to
put—to put on an animal. Okay, so it goes A-B-A. יש נוחלין
ומנחילין, Yesh nochalin u'manhilin, there are some people that inherit and bequeath,
נוחלין ולא מנחילין nochalin ve'lo manhilin who can inherit and not bequeath,
מנחילין ולא נוחלין, manhilin ve'lo nochalin, bequeath and not inherit, לא נוחלין
ולא מנחילין, lo nochalin ve'lo manhilin, not—not inherit nor bequeath. ומפרש אלו
נוחלין ומנחילין ברישא U'me'faresh elu nochalin u'manhilin be'reisha and it started with
the first, there was A-B-C-D and it started with A. אלא, Ela,
so you see it doesn't always pick up with the last thing.
So anyway, what's the rule? אלא לעולם תנא הכי ותנא הכי. Ela
le'olam tana hachi ve'tana hachi. You're right. Sometimes it starts off—it goes
with the A and sometimes it goes with the
B. אלא התם דאיסורא דנפשיה הוא מפרש איסורא דנפשיה ברישא. Ela hatam
de'issura de'nafshai hu me'faresh issura de'nafshai be'reisha. When it's talking about what
you're allowed to or not allowed to do, can you go out
on שבת Shabbat with certain clothes, what can you use to light
candles? So it starts with the things you're not allowed to do,
it's about you personally, we want to focus on "don't do this."
So we say this you can and this you can't, here are
the things you can't. We want to focus on what you can't
do. גבי בהמה דאיסורא אדי בהמה הוא דאתי, Gabei behemah de'issura adei
behemah hu de'ati, by the animal where it's not you who's doing
it, it's just your animal who's doing it, מפרש היתירא ברישא, me'faresh
ateira be'reisha, we don't have to start by saying "don't do". this,
it's only your animal, so we can start saying your animal can
do the following, which is a little funny. Who cares really, me
or the animal, either way I'm the one who's responsible. But also,
that doesn't explain the נוחלין ומנחילין, nochlin u'manchilin, right? That says by
the בהמה behemah we started first with the things the animal can
do because it's not you. Okay, but by the case about inheriting
and bequeathing, it starts not with the last thing it left off
from, but it goes back to the top of the list. So
this answer isn't going to work for everything, so let's keep on
reading. גבי יש נוחלין נמי gabei yesh nochlin nami and by the
list of inheriting and bequeathing,
מפרש עיקר נחלה ברישא. mefarsha ikar nachala bereisha. It starts with the
things that are the primary. It'd rather tell you people that can
inherit and bequeath, which is the classic case before it gets to
the exceptions. So basically what it's saying is, whether we do A-B-B-A
or whether we do A-B-A-B, it depends on the case. Some cases
it makes sense we want to start with the A, other cases
we want to start with the B. So what's the story here?
Why would you do כינוי kinuy, יד yad, יד yad, כינוי? kinuy.
So now we need a logic why we want to illustrate יד
yad first. So let's take a look. אלא הכא לפרושי כינויי ברישא.
ella hacha leperushei kinnuyei bereisha. Why here then, if you need a
reason for each case, why here should we not start illustrating with
the כינויים? kinnuyim? Why would we do the יד? yad? אלא
היינו טעמא ידות הוה דאתו ליה מדרשה חביבי ליה ella haynu ta'ama
yadot hava de'atu leh midrashah chavivi leh because the idea that a
יד yad works, an elliptical statement works, is learned out from a
פסוק. pasuk. This was in the גמרא Gemara about, you know, in
נדרים, Nedarim, we've learned this out from a פסוק. pasuk. So therefore,
and
since we learned it out from a פסוק, pasuk, we'd rather talk
about the things that were learned from rabbinic derivation that has a
special place in our heart. Okay, that we'd rather talk about the
יד yad first. Of course the question is going to be if
you'd rather talk about the יד yad first, right? Right, everybody got
sort of guesses? I know I'm going a little fast but it's
gotten a little late, I'm sorry. Anyway, so it's like AB, right?
If it were כל כינויי נזירות kol kinnuyei nezirot and then we
stuck in
the
world, you know, if כל ידות נזירות kol yadot nezirot as well
נזירות. neziros I don't know, yes, fine. Okay anyway, we stuck that
in, and then the example was אהא, aha,
right? Which is a יד. yad. And then it said, right, it
said אהא נזיח אהא פזיח,
aha nazich aha
pazich, whatever, etc., which is a, which is a כינוי. kinnuy. Wait
what? Whatever, yeah well I don't know which one אהא aha goes
into. Okay anyway, okay so the point is we stuck this phrase
in and then we said, okay, then why did it? But even
if we're going to stick this in, shouldn't you illustrate the כינויים
kinnuyim first? So it said no, sometimes we pick up with, we
do it in the A-B-B-A. So it says okay, but sometimes we
do A-B-A-B. What's the logic? So it says we'd rather do this
first because this is learned from a דרשה. drashah. Okay, I mean
we're not quoting the דרשה drashah here, but from a פסוק pasuk
we learn the idea that a יד yad counts. So when we
learn things rabbinically, when the rabbis derive things from פסוקים, pesukim, it
has a special place in their heart and they'd rather talk about
it first. Of course if they'd rather talk about it first, why
not talk about it first here in the, in the broad statement
before you get to the concrete one? So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, wonderful. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא
היינו טעמא ידות הוה דאתו ליה מדרשה חביבי ליה. ella haynu ta'ama
yadot hava de'atu leh midrashah chavivi leh. וליפתח בהו ברישא, veliftach behu
bereisha, why not have that as the opening statement? So תנא כי
מתחיל מתחיל בעיקר קרבן. tanna ki matchil matchil be'ikar korban. No, no,
no, because when you start, you want to start about the thing
that is the primary. Now קרבן korban is a funny word here,
but it basically means the primary act of נזירות, neziros right? The
more fundamental, and somehow using a substitute term, even though that, as
we pointed out, like it might even be a made-up language, but
since it's a full sentence and it's just about interpreting what the
terms mean, that's seen as a more fundamental idea. And a יד,
yad, which is a partial sentence, is a bigger חידוש. chiddush. I
mean the very fact that you needed a דרשה drashah to tell
you יד yad and you don't need a דרשה drashah to tell
you a כינוי kinnuy shows you that כינוי kinnuy is a more,
you know, it's a more basic, fundamental concept. So we would rather
start with the idea of כינוי, kinnuy, which is just substitute terms
and you don't need a דרשה drashah for that. That's just saying,
okay, use נזיח, it means נזיר. nazir... Okay, so that's a more
basic idea. This is a bigger חידוש. chiddush And the fact, the
proof that it's a bigger חידוש chiddush is we needed a דרשה.
drashah. So because we needed a דרשה, drashah, we like דרשות, drashot,
we'll start with it as an example, as a concrete example, but
because it is less obvious, we're going to start with the more
obvious one. Okay, חביבין ליה וליפתח בהו וכי מתחיל מתחיל בעיקר קרבן
ומפרש ידות ברישא. chavivin leh veliftach behu veki matchil matchil be'ikar korban
umefarash yadot bereisha. And then when it comes to illustrating it, we
start with
the idea of ידות. yadot. And making it clear that although the
משנה *Mishna* isn't clear about this, there are two categories in the
משנה *Mishna*. Let's get now to some of the actual meat of
the discussion. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says האומר אהא הרי
זה נזיר nazir, *Ha-omer ehai harei zeh Nazir*. So here's the יד
*yad* case, I will be, without the fill in the blank, you
are a נזיר *Nazir*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דדילמא אהא
בתענית קאמר *d-dilma ehai be-ta'anis qamar*, how do you know how to
fill in the blank? Maybe it means I'll be in a, I'll
accept upon myself a תענית *ta'anis*, or who knows whatever other a
million things you could be saying. But even an act of הפלאה
*hafla'ah*, a verbal act that creates a status, doesn't have to be
נזיר *Nazir*, could be putting yourself into a תענית *ta'anis*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר שמואל Shmuel. כגון שהיה נזיר עובר לפניו
lefanav, *amar Shmuel kegon she-hayah Nazir over lefanav*. There was a נזיר
*Nazir* walking in front of you, and since there was a נזיר
*Nazir* walking in front of you, the context makes it clear. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לימא קסבר שמואל Shmuel ידים שאינן
מוכיחות לא הויין ידים *leima kasavar Shmuel yadayim she-einan mokhichos lo havyon
yadayim*. So ידים *yadayim* here is a יד *yad*, an elliptical sentence.
So now there's a question, if somebody says a fully elliptical sentence,
how the heck do we know what they mean? Right? So there
are three stages within the idea of יד
*yad*. There's a יד מוכיח yad mokiach. *yad mokhiach*. If you want
to know the best example of a יד מוכיח yad mokiach? *yad
mokhiach*, and this is actually partly where this discussion of שמואל *Shmuel*
comes from, somebody says under the חופה *chuppah* to a woman הרי
את מקודשת *harei at mekudeshes* and he doesn't say לי *li*. Okay,
so who knows, maybe he's just a שליח *shaliach* for somebody. Okay,
but the fact that he's there with his whole family and he's
wearing a tux or whatever, you know, it's pretty much a יד
מוכיח *yad mokhiach* that he means לי *li*. He didn't say it,
but the context makes it very, very clear what he meant. That's
יד מוכיח *yad mokhiach*. There's a יד שאינו מוכיח yad she'eino mokiach,
*yad she-eino mokhiach*, which is that, and there's a, and there's a
not a יד *yad*, okay? It's so, it's so unclear that something
isn't a יד *yad*. So an example of not a יד *yad*,
which is I think אהא *ehai*, I will be, with no context
isn't even a יד *yad*. You could fill in that sentence in
a million ways. We don't even begin to speculate what you mean.
A יד שאינו מוכיח yad she'eino mokiach. *yad she-eino mokhiach* means you
probably meant you want to be a נזיר *Nazir*, but it's not
clear, we have some questions, maybe, maybe not, but it's probably what
you meant. Okay. So the question is when, a יד שאינו מוכיח
yad she'eino mokiach *yad she-eino mokhiach*, does that work? Okay. Is that
included in in ידים *yadayim*? If the somebody, is that, it's pretty
clear he says, let's say he even says afterwards, "Yes, that's what
I meant," but at the time the words themselves even taken with
context were not obvious that that's what you meant. Is that also
work? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so לימא קסבר שמואל *leima
kasavar Shmuel*, שמואל *Shmuel* says נזיר עובר לפניו *Nazir over lefanav* works.
Maybe he says ידים שאינן מוכיחות לא הויין ידים *leima kasavar Shmuel
yadayim she-einan mokhichos lo havyon yadayim*. Since he had to give the
case that the נזיר *Nazir* was walking in front of you, the
גמרא *Gemara* assumes that a נזיר *Nazir* walking in front of you
is a יד מוכיח *yad mokhiach*. And since that was the example
he gave you where it was obvious, so presumably if it was
less obvious than that, it would not be good enough. יד שאינו
מוכיח yad she'eino mokiach. *yad she-eino mokhiach* presumably would not work. It
would have to be very obvious for שמואל *Shmuel* in order for
it to count. Does this what שמואל *Shmuel* hold? And the reason
it's asking is because there's a discussion in קידושין *Kiddushin* basically exactly
what I said, the person said הרי את מקודשת *harei at mekudeshes*
and he didn't say לי *li*, okay, where the גמרא *Gemara*, where
שמואל *Shmuel* also discusses does it work or not work? So there's
an ongoing question, does שמואל *Shmuel* believe that you need יד מוכיח
*yad mokhiach* or is יד אינו מוכיח *yad eino mokhiach* enough? And
by saying a נזיר *Nazir* walking in front, it sounds like that
that would be a very obvious מוכיח *mokhiach*. So does that mean
anything less than that would not work? So אמרי *amri* no. בזמן
שנזיר עובר לפניו ליכא לספוקי במילתא אחרינא *bizman she-Nazir over lefanav, lekka
le-sefukei be-milsa achrina*. When a נזיר *Nazir* is walking in front, there's
no other doubt. Okay, which sort of says it's a יד מוכיח
*yad mokhiach*, which is what we were saying. But וודאי *vaddi*, but
here's the kicker, אין נזיר עובר לפניו *ein Nazir over lefanav*, but
if there isn't a נזיר *Nazir* walking in front, אמרינן דילמא אהא
בתענית קאמר *amrina dilma ehai be-ta'anis qamar*. Maybe he, maybe you mean
I'll be in a תענית *ta'anis*. Now that wasn't really answer the
question. Okay, but it seems like what the גמרא *Gemara* is saying
is that that without a נזיר עובר לפניו *Nazir over lefanav*, it
wouldn't be a יד *yad* at all. So right, if you just
say אהא *ehai*, that's אהא *ehai* what, a million things under the
sun. Okay, so yes, שמואל *Shmuel* gave an example of נזיר עובר
לפניו *Nazir over lefanav*, and that might even be a יד מוכיח
*yad mokhiach* for all we know, but it doesn't prove what שמואל
*Shmuel*'s position is by יד שאינו מוכיח yad she'eino mokiach *yad she-eino
mokhiach*, right? Is that clear? If you just said I will be,
that's not even a יד *yad*. So שמואל *Shmuel* had to, he
could say the משנה *Mishna* means what it sounds like, because that's
not even a יד *yad*. So he gave an example of נזיר
עובר לפניו *Nazir over lefanav*. Alright, but what does that say about
about a middle case? If we could construct a middle case, that's
less obvious what would שמואל *Shmuel* hold by a יד שאינו מוכיח
yad she'eino mokiach *yad she-eino mokhiach*? Alright, so we don't really know
the story of יד שאינו מוכיח *yad she-eino mokhiach*. Now the גמרא
*Gemara* continues. I'm simplifying it a little bit, but that's the differences
רש"י *Rashi* or pseudo-רש"י *pseudo-Rashi* and תוספות *Tosfos*, but that's
the
bottom line. Okay, בדילמא לפטור מן קרבנותיו, even if a נזיר is
over לפניו, now the גמרא like shifts gears. A minute until now
we've been assuming it's a יד מוכיח. The גמרא's going to say
who even says it's a יד מוכיח? A נזיר is walking in
front of you and you say I will be, maybe it means
I will commit
to providing the קרבנות for that נזיר and we're going to see
that you can actually do that. Sounds strange that somebody else's obligation,
how can you accept their קרבן korban obligation on you? But that
possibility actually is there. So maybe what you're saying is let it
be on me, not נזירות, but his
קרבן korban obligation.
לפטור את הנזיר, liftor es hanazir, yeah,
I'm going to bring the קרבנות to exempt this guy. So even
with a נזיר לפניו, Nazir lefanav, maybe it's a יד שאינו מוכיח,
okay, and so maybe the answer could be yes it may be
it is, but maybe that's good enough because still so let's see
what the גמרא answers דקאמר בלבו dekamar belibo because he said, okay,
there was a little bit of a doubt and then we asked
him afterwards and we said what did you mean? And he said
yeah I meant I want to be a נזיר. So the גמרא
says אי הכי מאי למימרא? ei hachi mai lemimra? If that's true
then it's obvious, he told us he wanted to be a נזיר
afterwards when we asked him. No, מהו דתימא בעינן פיו ולבו שוים
קמשמע לן. mahu deseima bainan piv ulibo shavin kamashma lan. I might
think you need his words
and his thoughts to be in sync קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. Now
again, like we were saying before by תוספות by the whole idea
of you don't have to mean it, everybody points out it is
not קמשמע לן kamashma lan you don't have to have your words
and your thoughts in sync. The most basic assumption of נדרים Nedarim
and נזירות is you have to intend it and you have to
say it and they have to be in sync. What it means
is I might think that he needs everything to be explicit, okay,
קמשמע לן kamashma lan that it doesn't need to be fully explicit.
He said he meant נזיר, the words had a little bit were
a little
ambiguous, but they probably meant נזיר, and he clarified that they did
mean נזיר. So that is enough with his additional clarification to say
that that's what he said. Okay, now that's important ultimately if you
think about it, that's a way of articulating exactly the problem of
יד שאינו מוכיח. יד שאינו מוכיח is did you say it or
not? Well, that's probably how we would have interpreted what you said,
but we're not a hundred percent sure it's not like the words
even in context are completely transparent. So does that count as a
speech act if the words even in context are not a hundred
percent clear? And the חידוש is yes it does. Since you intended
it and then afterwards we clarified that that's what you meant, so
the fact that you intended it and you clarified that's what you
meant, we can now say that that is what the words actually
were saying. Okay, but that is a perfect illustration of יד שאינו
מוכיח. Not only did you not fully say it, it wasn't even
fully clear that that's what you meant. It was pretty clear, but
not fully clear. And that's enough of an official statement, official act
of speech, a יד שאינו מוכיח when it is joined with your
clarification that comes afterwards. Okay, so that seems to be the conclusion
here actually, very consistent, that this actually is a יד שאינו מוכיח
and it works according to שמואל. There is a general question whether
שמואל rules יד מוכיח יד שאינו מוכיח, yad mokiach yad she'eino mokiach,
but that very much seems to be the presumption here.
Yes, the problem is this is not what פיו ולבו שוים piv
ulibo shavin generally mean.
Right, so the ראשונים say it means I might think that this
isn't a full act of פה peh and that what you said
in your heart doesn't matter because, right, so we're reframing exactly what
the statement means, but as I
said, but the weakness of
yeah I mean otherwise though nobody can conclude that you don't need
to intend what you're saying, okay, or that it only goes by
what you're thinking and you don't need to say anything because that's
clearly not true. The most basic principle of נדרים Nedarim and נזירות
is you need to think it and you need to say it
and they need to be in sync.
Okay, so we will end with this for now. I'll just say
maybe one very brief statement what I shared earlier about נזיר about
just a very just one minute in terms
of my mother עליה השלום aleha hashalom חנה בת מרדכי אליעזר.
Chana bas Mordechai Eliezer. We're about to see tomorrow, I was hoping
we would get to today, that there's a question about whether you
know נזיר is a חוטא choteh or not a חוטא, choteh, a
sinner or not a sinner, and the normal explanation in the גמרא
why the נזיר is a חוטא choteh is because he's denying themselves
the pleasure of the world. But I actually think that there's a
different understanding and it gets to the core question of what a
person thinks is a primary form of like religious engagement in the
world. You know, does a person become reach spiritual heights by separating
from the world? You let your hair grow wild so you're an
outcast of society, you don't come in contact with dead, you don't
sort of engage in any sense of like physical existence to try
to separate yourself from the physical reality as much as possible. You
know, that's one sense of קדושה, kedusha, but there's a... It’s a
very different idea of קדושה, kedushah, which is like to fully engage
in the world and, you know, and as רבי ישראל סלנטר Rabbi
Yisrael Salanter said, he says, you know, the great line is יענעמס
גשמיות איז דיין רוחניות. Yenems Gashmius is dayn Ruchnius. The other person’s,
you know, physical needs are your spiritual needs, and that the way
of a real full expression of קדושה kedushah is in terms of,
you know, not separating from society but being engaged and to really
understand people’s very real physical needs. And my mother עליה השלום, aleha
hashalom, you know, some of I think the greatest image I have
of her was when, you know, like her answering calls literally in
the middle of the night—midnight, later, whatever—about somebody passed away, needing to
arrange a טהרה, taharah, to go, go run and to do the
טהרה. taharah. I mean, this is being מטמא למתים, metamei lemeitim, which,
you know, the נזיר... so for the נזיר, how you become holy
is you separate yourself from this. But you know, a true holiness
is how we extend ourselves even, you know, for, you know, for
people even, you know, even in these times when there’s no one
else there, and that we understand, you know, what, that this is,
this is life and this is death and this is what, where
our responsibilities and our obligations lie. And just in terms of issues
of like, you know, הנאת עולם הזה, hana'at olam hazeh, a lot
of people said to us at the שבעה, shivah, you know, that
what was so powerful that when they moved into the community that
my mother was, you know, was the one to welcome them into
the home and make them feel, you know, you know, invited and
welcome and, you know, providing food, taking care of them, and in
particular that like even like some of myself and my siblings and
our when our friends would come after being—not having been at the
house for like a year, two years, my mom would remember what
was their favorite dish and make sure to make it for them
on שבת. Shabbat. You know what that does to tell somebody that
they matter and they’re cared for and they’re loved, it’s very, very
powerful, and a real sense of קדושה kedushah comes, you know, not
from separating from this world but knowing how to engage in this
world and to understand our people, human beings, and our real needs,
and to and to really attend to them and touch people and,
you know, and and make people feel, feel, feel welcomed and cared
for. So may her memory always be for a blessing.